before we go into how virtual memory
Works let's for see why do we even want
to have virtual memory and the short
answer is that we want to have virtual
memory because the programmer and the
hardware have different views of what
memory means in the hardware view the
machine has some memory modules with an
actual amount of memory that can be
accessed by the real processor let's say
that this module is 2 GB and this module
is 2 GB
so what the hardware really has is 4 GB
of memory and the addresses for this 4
GB are going to be 0 through 4 GB in
contrast the programmer's view of memory
is that it's a huge array with addresses
that go from zero to a very very large
number if it's a 64-bit machine this is
many many gigabytes obviously this is
much more than what the machine really
has
some of this memory might be reserved
for the system some of this memory
contains the actual program instructions
some of it is for static data then we
have the memory for the Heap which is
where maloc Finds Its memory and this
Heap can grow and then some of it
usually very high in the memory address
space is the stack and that typically
grows this way but the programmer
doesn't really want to be bothered by
how much space is there between the Heap
and the stack what they want to do is
simply maloc or push things on the stack
and they never run out of memory and in
a 64-bit address space chances are they
won't actually run out of memory but the
problem is the actual amount of memory
that they're using might be less or it
might be much more than the actual
memory that the machine has here things
are actually much more complicated
because we typically don't run only one
program on a machine we actually are
simultaneously having multiple programs
run you might be having something that
browses files here an MP3 player playing
in the background and the word processor
here each of these sees the address
space that begins at zero and ends at a
very large address we don't want to
write our programs so that this needs to
run as the first program in the system
this needs to run as the second program
in the system you want to write a
program as if it was the only program in
the system and then just run multiple
programs like that but that means that
this program's idea of memory is it
thinks it has all of this memory this
program similarly thinks it has all of
this memory so as far as these two
programs are concerned for example their
code might well be at the same address
in each program although in fact they
have different instructions at those
addresses so virtual ual memory is a way
of
reconciling how the programmer's view
Memory and how the hardware actually
needs to view Memory in order to work